hey guys welcome to future thinkers
podcast episode number 43 this is the
second half of our interview with Daniel
schmuck Tim Berger who is the co-founder
of neuro hacker collective and this half
we talk about the process of
neurogenesis which parts of ancient
wisdom are useful in modern society
therapeutic use of psychedelics and
rites of passage and many other
fascinating things for all the links
mentions and books from this episode go
to future thinkers or x-43 and to listen
to the first half go to future thinkers
org slash 42 and if you haven't listened
to our other episode with Daniel smoked
tuna burger in which we talked about the
global phase shift we may be going
through go to future thinkers at work /
36 and if you're interested in trying
qualia the smart drug stack that Daniels
company has developed go to future
thinkers org slash brain hack oh one
word before we get into this episode I
want to say thank you to our recent
patrons and donors Christian Pablo and
Richard
you guys are awesome thank you for
helping us make this show possible
alright let's get into it
welcome to future thinkers org a podcast
about the evolution of technology
society and consciousness I'm Mike
Gilliland
and I'm UV Ivanova to get notified of
new podcasts and videos go to future
thinkers org and subscribe to our
mailing list you can also find us on
iTunes stitcher and you tube if you like
what we do and you want to help us make
more podcasts and videos give us a like
or review share it with your friends and
consider becoming a patron go to
patreon.com/crashcourse org slash bap
last but not least if you want to get
access to more content hidden episodes
or if you just want to chat with us in
previous guests then check out our
community at community dot future
thinkers org
[Music]
I'd like to go back to neurogenesis and
maybe talk again about some of the more
specific treatments that support
neurogenesis and I'm also wondering is
this work mostly being done in in the
space of alzheimerís treatment no
neurogenesis a fascinating field adult
neurogenesis in particular because you
know up until not that long ago it was
commonly believed that we didn't
generate new neurons after adulthood and
that's not true
- why neurogenesis is so fascinating we
our brain does continuously produce
neural stem cells most in the
hippocampus that then differentiate into
you know other regions of the brain
other tissues and that that rate of
neural stem cell production can be
increased or decreased by a number of
factors so when we think about brain
aging and also neurogenesis isn't just
for brain aging it's also for dealing
with traumatic brain injury and the
ability to actually heal areas of brain
that were damaged it has to do with
increasing gray matter density and just
increasing the total information
processing capacity of the system also
dealing with you know nerve damage
peripheral nerve damage or neuro
degeneration research on our team just
wrote a meta-analysis of all of the
research done on addled neurogenesis and
we'll be publishing it soon and it is
it's fascinating and our hypothesis from
evolutionary biology perspective is that
when you think about human genetics and
what they selected for more than
anything they selected for this is a
generalized but fair way to say it
they selected for neurogenesis you know
our genes selected for memes right they
selected for a creature that could
change themselves and their basis for
acting over the course of their life
significantly in one generation to the
next faster than genes could change and
so most animals their behavior is pretty
genetically hardwired and modulated by
the environments a little which is why
they actually have the hardwired code to
like get up and walk
do stuff in the first few minutes of
life and we are jnanis and basically
useless for so long right for a year and
a half we can do hardly anything and
it's because we're very soft wired
because as tool makers that modify our
own environment think about like the
most adaptive person 10,000 years ago at
spear-throwing would be useless today
because they couldn't text and they
couldn't type and they wouldn't know how
to call uber and and so it's very
important that as we are modifying the
environment we can adapt to our new
modified environments which means that
we are not hardwired that we can be
rewiring our innate processes right and
neurogenesis is a major part of that so
it's a super fascinating field for
disease recovery for anti-aging for
understanding human nature and for kind
of hyper learning and capabilities so
there's a bunch of things that affect
neurogenesis there are these chemicals
called neurotransmitters
BDNF is the most well understood one
brain drive neurotrophic factor ng F for
nerve growth factor so there are things
that can increase BDNF increase NGS and
normal lifestyle things like exercise is
one of the ones that we know better than
anything that actually increases
neurogenesis weight lifting and hit
training in particular more than
aerobics are very BDNF up regulating
sleep is BDNF up regulating and lack of
sleep ins of meaning decrease
neurogenesis there are a number of
nutrients that are also involved and
there are some herbs and mushrooms that
have very very potent effects so you
know lion's mane has been used for nerve
injury for a long time and it happens to
very acutely elevate ngf levels some key
nutrients like methylcobalamin
methylated coma b12 and taurine in
fairly high doses up regulate the
endogenous rate of neurogenesis then
there are some drugs that are being
developed forward neurogenic purposes
and I actually think this is one of the
most brilliant things a drug could do
you know I said some things that sounded
like they were negative regarding
pharmaceutical approach as a whole
earlier I want to say that some very
meaningfully positive things are
happening in all branches of
pharmaceuticals largely because other
areas especially in complex disease are
failing so that what's the cool new
areas that are happening is not just a
chemical that will try and change the
level of something but a drug that will
actually support the body's ability to
do something better so that I can make
this point well think about a statin
right for cholesterol if your
cholesterol is high and we give you a
statin to lower it we don't know why
your cholesterol is high your
cholesterol can be high because of diet
it can be high because of diabetes like
things it can be high because of mold
toxicity and so just lowering it doesn't
actually address the pathology or the
behavior that whatever so that kind of
drug approach is not that interesting
and very interestingly sometimes the
opposite is what needs to happen so we
can you know if your blood pressure's
high we give you a drug to just lower
your blood pressure all right you just
exogenous lis lower blood pressure but
why had the body been setting that point
too high to begin with if you exercise
the reason that exercise lowers blood
pressure is because when you exercise it
raises your blood pressure and when the
blood pressure spikes even higher it
actually kicks in the hormetic
mechanisms hormesis is the body's
response to stress it kicks in the
hormetic mechanism for the body to say
oh the blood pressures too high let's
bring it down on our own and the body
starts regulating blood pressure better
but it actually rather than externally
moving it lower what it needed was to be
moved higher and then it and its own
self-regulation occurred so drugs that
just try and move something into range
without asking why it happened and
without increasing the body's ability to
maintain that range not so interesting
to me even though I mean they're
life-saving they're just not adequate
solutions as we move forward but as we
move from like the chemo therapeutic
approaches to cancer to amino oncology
immuno oncology is the beginning of us
doing anything with cancer that's really
interesting where we're actually
training the body's immune systems
capacity to kill cancer cells better
that's actually pretty great well in the
neural
logic space there's a company called
neural stem they're working on a drug
there and I believe face two clinical
trials right now called NS I 189 and it
was originally being developed for ALS
but now I believe that the first thing
that are trying to improve it for his
major depressive disorder but it for ALS
they were originally working with neural
stem cells they would grow neural stem
cells and shoot him up into the spinal
cord either where there was spinal cord
injury or you know degeneration like a
ALS and they were getting some results
and they wanted to say well could we
increase the body's rate of producing
its own neural stem cells so they were
growing neural stem cells in vitro and
seeing if there were any molecules that
would increase their own proliferation
they found some that did an SI 189 was
the primary one so here it's a drug that
isn't trying to modulate an end chain
chemical it's actually up regulating
your body's own regulatory process and
once you have those new neural stem
cells they keep doing their thing right
they they become tissues and they do
their regulatory thing now if you think
about if that drug continues to succeed
and I don't know if it will but there
will be a whole class of ones like that
it could fix nerve damage from injury
nerve damage from neuropathy it could
fix retinopathy it could fix MS ALS
Parkinson's you know and the reason why
I was working in depression was as they
were getting up regulated production of
new stem cells in the hippocampus and
been that starting to affect the
surrounding basal structures the person
actually had more information processing
capacity to process their emotions and
process their experiences and they
didn't get overwhelmed you get depressed
by them there's a company called zing up
they have a website zing up comm and
they originally developed friend of mine
over there developed a set of processes
that they were trying to bring about for
helping autism and then what they
figured out they ended up applying to
just performance enhancement so right
now it's a performance enhancement site
but they
that there were you actually really dig
this they were movement patterns that
more than other movement patterns
radically up regulated neural stem cell
production and specifically were growing
gray matter density in the cerebellum
hippocampus pond mostly cerebellum Wow
and that autism was getting better
depression was getting better you know
they did a study in prisons and violence
went down because when people are
overwhelmed by the amount of stimulus
coming in their emotions etc and they
can't process at all then the results of
the not processed stuff is lingering
anxiety depression confusion and just
being able to process it better
physiologically led to you know the
healthier happier people and so how they
found to do it I think this is a kind of
profound insight was when you first
start doing a some kind of coordination
activity like riding a bike or walking
on a slackline or juggling that you've
never done at first it seems almost like
it's impossible like you can't even find
the place where it makes sense that that
will be possible because you don't have
the neural circuitry to do that
particular kind of balanced sensory
motor coordination stuff yet and then as
soon as you start to get it you're like
okay I'm not nowhere near perfect yet
but I have the hang like there's this
there's something inside of me that
knows how to do this going from the I
have no idea how to do this up to
getting the hang of it there is a rapid
rate of the production of new neural
stem cells they're saying whoa we're
actually in danger because we can't do
this physical activity that's obviously
you know needs to happen let's AB
regulate our capacity like crazy to be
able to do it once you can do it and now
you're just getting better doing it you
get a diminishing return on that and so
what they figured out to do was how to
take people through a series of
exercises and they customized them based
on assessment but in general anyone
could do this a series of exercises it
involved coordination and balance and
coordinating multiple sensory motor
groups that were super difficult and as
soon as you started to get the hang of
it they switched into a new one and then
as soon as you're sure to get the hang
of it they switched and did a new one so
you were maximizing for the great the
growth rate of neurogenesis which then
ended up having in effect on you know
all kinds of other things the hypothesis
there was that it has to do with
automating learning so we learn some you
know we start learning some motor
function and it's very hard and we're
trying to think about where our hands go
and where our feet go and all these
things at once and we can't think about
that many things consciously so our
brain has to try to get some of them in
unconscious memory you know and then we
can drive a stick-shift without even
thinking about it when at first it seems
like seven different hard things to
coordinate in an evolutionary
environment us moving stuff from
conscious to unconscious right conscious
consciously we're trying to learn some
new skills now we can unconsciously
perform it we would have done that for
motor tasks more than anything else and
cognitive and language etc tests kind of
came evolutionarily on top of that so
our capacity to learn new stuff motor
tasks are going to be able to drive that
evolutionary hardware more specifically
those are hypothesis and it seems to be
well supported by the evidence and so if
you do a bunch of sensory motor tasks
that you can't do it all and then you
start to be able to do them and you do a
bunch of different ones you're actually
increasing kind of the neural
infrastructure for the rate of learning
and automating conscious - unconscious
performance and then that same
infrastructure is used when you are
learning cognitive tasks or
interpersonal skills or anything else so
the idea was that it would increase rate
of learning and they've got a bunch of
research showing that happens to be the
case so that's another example of a of a
methodology approach right so you've got
drug approaches nutrition approaches
exercise approaches methodology
approaches for neurogenesis that is
fascinating I think that explains in
plain terms how yoga works and and how
yoga actually supports brain development
just through doing a series of different
complex movements totally I would say
yoga is probably a combination of that
effect that we just mentioned along with
stress relieving effects and some of the
effects of increased breath both
increased breath on parasympathetic
function and on oxygen carbon dioxide
levels very cool what are some of the
other areas that are important to talk
about so now to summarize we've talked
about the gut brain the emotional
regulation we've talked about movement
systems approaches to measuring and
understanding what is going on in your
body before you're going to go and mess
with it what are some other areas of
neural hacking that are really important
pillar areas we didn't talk about
altered states of consciousness yet all
right it's waiting for that one so
psychedelic assisted psychotherapy
psychedelic assisted spirituality
psychedelic assisted neural Repat
earning super fascinating field and you
know even though that field started with
you know people like stanislav grof etc
back in the day it has been it has been
accelerating a lot recently and i'm very
happy to see this and i think about the
role of psychedelics and the edge ins in
human development i think about three
kind of distinct categories you can use
it as a personal development tool you
can use as an interpersonal tool and as
a transpersonal tool so as a personal
tool we can talk about you know it's
their role in addiction recovery so
you've seen the results of ibogaine and
five Meo DMT being used along with
psychotherapeutic processes for
addiction recovery for people on opiates
on benzos on all kinds of things and
it's it's a fascinating field it shares
some things with ketamine's approach to
depression but you know so you can look
at addiction recovery work with PTSD
with end-of-life anxiety these are these
are areas where it seems to be having an
effect that is either more than or
different than any other therapies and
so
very fascinating this is for like you
know working on pathology for just more
kind of psychotherapeutic growth the
role that psychedelics can play in
shadow work and integrating parts of
self is really fascinating when you
realize that we don't remember when
we're remembering memories we don't
remember the memory we remember how its
consolidated in our brain factoring all
the times we've remembered it and
changed it that's a big insight because
it means that if you can re remember a
memory and remember it quite differently
you can actually affect how it was
stored in all the future times it will
be referenced and so say someone is on
MDMA and so they're in a pretty aforex
state and then they think about some
negative experience of their past but
they can't feel they can't feel negative
well they think about it so it would
always be in the past that they would
think about it and feel negative right
they have that associative conditioning
now they're thinking about it and
feeling great so that means that the
regions of the brain and the chemistry
that's involved in feeling great and
that specific thought or Co wiring
together and then the next time when
this person is sober and they think
about it they remember the last way they
remember it and it doesn't have that
same charge that it used to have for
them this can be about a traumatic
memory of the past it can also be
thinking about parts of themselves that
they're ashamed of or can't love or
whatever and instantly like in a fairly
short amount of time one or a small
number of sessions radically change the
charge around psychological topics this
is something I've been really interested
in in and thinking about and partially
why I brought up the whole idea of the
gut brain and asking your gut how you
feel about something because I'm trying
to separate how I feel and what I think
about memories and about how I look into
the future so this has been an extremely
useful tool for me because I separate
the memory into its two components and
then process the emotions on their own
so that I don't have to continue feeling
negatively about an event yeah that
worked really well you know because you
have the memory of just
what happened and then you have all the
meaning-making around it and the
meaning-making can change while you
still remember the event that happened
and when the meaning-making changes the
cymatics and the emotions can change
accordingly right so you experience some
event in childhood and the meaning was
something about that you're a failure
and you should never try stuff and
whatever and when you reprocess and say
actually that's not a realistic meaning
I was a kid and you know I have actually
done well of those things later etcetera
you can still remember the event but it
doesn't have the same Associated meaning
about self and about reality so then it
doesn't have the same charge the fear
charge that's trying to protect you from
that painful possibility in the future
etc you can do that without psychedelics
psychedelics just happened to be one
very fast way to change that association
yeah I think psychotherapy is another
one and also hypnotherapy because you
can induce somebody into trance and then
reom print the certain experience so
that exactly like you were saying the
processing of it changes how your brain
processes that so when you talk about
hypnotherapy and inducing trance if
we're going to try and change the way
that someone has stored of memory or
change their association with a phobia
or whatever it is then we want to get
them into a state that is amenable to
change right psychedelics are a good way
of doing this largely because they
actually increased neuroplasticity so we
talked about neurogenesis developing new
neurons but developing new synapses and
cleaning old synapses might be even more
meaningful which is what in the brain
interconnects with with what so old
synapses that are no longer relevant can
get cleaved mostly during deep sleep by
microglia and then new synapses get
developed it's called synaptogenesis
through the learning process so like
that zing up example as you go from
can't find it at all to find it that's
the process of synaptic formation and
then healthy synapses that are doing
something effective get re supported
through something called the long term
potential
process that says yes this is still a
good synapse and wanted to keep
operating automatically so let's keep
strengthening it so one of the things
many psychedelics do from a
neurophysiologic point of view is
increased neuroplasticity that's one of
our best understandings of one of the
things that's happening and that would
mean increased ability to actually
change neuro structural associations
with whatever you do next so if that's
the case it would make a lot of sense
why when someone has a bad trip it can
be so lastingly hard for them and when
someone has a really powerful trip it
can be so permanently changing for them
is because what was happening during
that time was having more net impact on
their brain than is usually capable of
happening per unit time right right
interesting
so psychedelics can do that breath work
right like the holotropic breathwork can
create a state of increased
susceptibility you can use strobe lights
to try and drive specific brainwave
patterns sleep deprivation
creates increased susceptibility which
is you know technique military issues
and even like some conferences use yeah
so I would say in general different
forms of psychotherapy are trying to
change our information process and
change our meaning making or cymatics or
emotion when you start to work on the
brain side and the psyche side together
you can get synergistically compounding
effects so think about this this is a
fun example if you do psychedelics and
then you are in a set or setting that is
not appropriate and you end up just
freaking out and then you kind of wire
that you're unsafe in a dangerous
universe that's lame right which is why
instead of underlings in matter which is
the difference between just tripping and
actually doing psychedelic assisted
psychotherapy or personal development
but if you take psychedelics and so now
imagery is very intense well you can do
better guided imagery work and you can
be in some image so you're going to go
back into regression work thing about
childhood but when you're visualizing it
you can actually
visualizing it sensorial and real so it
actually rewires more powerfully
plasticity is increased and you can even
do a micro dose right a micro dose where
you're still pretty much sober but
plasticity has increased which is why
people use micro dosing when they're
gonna go learn new athletic capabilities
or language whatever for
you know just rate of learnings of
plasticity say to micro dose then you do
some psychotherapy or EEG neurofeedback
or anything that's gonna be changing
neural patterns and then afterwards you
do things that chemically increase long
term potentiation and help lock in those
new patterns so that they actually stay
that would be like
cholinergic and there's a handful of
things that support the long term
potentiation process but we can just say
mostly cholinergic for now that sequence
of things is gonna have synergistic
value beyond what any of those things
have on their own right increased
plasticity to change old patterns put in
input to change old patterns to new
patterns put in chemical inputs and lock
in those new healthy adaptive patterns
so this is just starting to scratch on
what interesting neural hacking can look
like that is fascinating I mean this
kind of multi-tiered approach to
psychedelic therapy as opposed to
tripping like I said right I wonder how
this relates to the shamanic and
initiative practices of the past where
it was a kind of a multi tiered approach
to this profound consciousness change
that they were trying to achieve where
on one hand you have a shaman that is
guiding you then on the other hand you
have the the herb the psychoactive
ingredient that you're taking and then
on the other hand you have some sort of
stress testing so you have sleep
deprivation or physical exertion or
facing dangerous environments and then
after the person goes through this you
have the integration practices where
everybody hugs and you know the person
comes back to the tribe and you kind of
have the supportive environment that
probably releases some brain chemicals
for integrating this experience and
retaining it I wonder how we can take
this sort of multi tier approach and
apply it to modern life with better
technology
it's the same as you were mentioning
with that
it sounded like yoga had some of the
similar properties what I was saying
with the zing up neuroscience you know
for 250,000 years give or take the same
brains as we have now so they've been
smart people around for a long time
named and as they were paying attention
to what worked and didn't work and then
being able to pass that information down
over a long period of time they figured
out stuff that worked and so there's
certainly some stuff in the ancient
traditions where we figured out much
better stuff and there's some stuff
where their methods are still meaningful
and ways where there's nothing in modern
life like them and so obviously the
integration of understanding our
evolutionary biology and just just our
biology of ancient past understanding
what the ancient wisdom cultures figured
out that was meaningful and then being
able to not override that but add to
enhance that with what we know and are
going to know from all of the
disciplines of science and advancing
technology and exponential technology is
a right integrative approach so in your
opinion which aspects of this kind of
shamanic initiation practices do we have
today that we can enhance with modern
technology and what are the aspects that
we have seemingly lost that should be
brought back or kept as in the same way
that they were doing it before all right
well let's start with things that some
wisdom cultures and digitus cultures had
and I don't want to over romanticize
that their versions of these were
perfect or that all cultures had them
there's obviously a whole mix of things
there's some very meaningful stuff that
we have lost it needs to be
reincorporated in some way rites of
passage is an example so the rite of
passage there were many different rites
of passage that happened you know in
childhood when the child became
self-sufficient in some ways that could
be a rite of passage to recognize it
sometimes they got a different name at
that point rite of passage of puberty
and acknowledging what that meant our
children growing up through puberty
are experiencing their interest changes
their body changed there's so many
things and we just don't do anything to
acknowledge it and what we do do to
acknowledge it usually just makes it
feel worse right we show them videos of
gonorrhea and call it sex ed you know
and all the rites of passage the rites
of passages in menopause I have a friend
that is a one of the top evolutionary
biologists and he was saying that in his
assessment one of the interesting ways
to assess the wisdom of a culture is the
role of postmenopausal women in the
leadership of that culture and that
women after menopause who can't give
birth who can't make more babies but who
are still wired towards you know so have
evolutionary wiring towards mothering
have a unique capacity that neither
premenopausal women or men have which is
to be able to hold a mother energy
towards the whole that when you have
young kids it can still be easy to be a
little self-centered to you and your
kids but when you don't have young kids
anymore and yet you still have a
mothering energy to be able to hold the
whole whether it's the whole tribe or
expansively the whole biosphere etc you
know so like that's a rite of passage
that we mostly just think of as a bummer
that you know she needs Botox now rather
than any meaningful kind of thing so how
we just understand life and the phases
of life and the roles rites of passage
pretty much all of the wisdom cultures
did something better than we do and and
I don't mean that there was nothing
barbaric but there there were some
really beautiful things to that's one
example
another key example was they understood
that there is a difference between
comfort and happiness and they
understood that happiness oftentimes
required beings that were resilient to
discomfort and here's my narrative for
this after the Scientific Revolution
science was just awesome for so many
things but the point of the challenges
became so what's real is what's
measurable and if something isn't
measurable you can't do anything really
with it
and comfort was an easier to measure
thing than happiness was right we could
kind of objectively measure how
comfortable mattresses were and how good
the shock systems and cars were and
transport be able to measure evolution
in those ways but measuring individual
human happiness is a much trickier thing
to do and so you can see how much we
like people have physical comforts now
even just average people that Kings
didn't have in the past and yet we have
rampant mental illness that we also
didn't have in the past and one of the
interesting things that you notice most
wisdom cultures is that they have
practices that intentionally induced
meaningful discomfort to teach people to
be resilient emotionally to discomfort
so when you think about what a sweat
lodge was or what a Vision Quest was or
even what hatha yoga is like yoga I
don't want to say this is all yoga is
but if you just think about yoga through
the lens of get in a really awkward pose
and then find your breath and find peace
and then get in another really awkward
pose and find your breath and find peace
and get bent out of shape in all these
different ways and realize that wherever
you are you can find your breath and
find equanimity find peace you're
actually somatically imprinting that no
matter what kind of position you're put
into you can find your breath and find
peace in any of them that's an amazing
insight as people learn that their inner
state doesn't have to be affected by the
environment as much that leads to more
resilient happy people as you have
people that are only focused on making
their environment as comfortable as
possible you can get people who are
profoundly unresolved
right psychologically so this is another
thing that I would say wisdom cultures
had that we have largely lost is the
distinction between comfort and
happiness and the importance of
optimizing for happiness so that we
don't have to actually have a lot of
real suffering you have to actually just
induce nondamaging discomfort that's
another example that is just really not
part of our wisdom there are so many
things
if you think about the fact that they
were all you know a hundred and fifty
person tribes right Dunbar number of
tribes from an attachment theory point
of view you had secure attachment to 150
people those people weren't leaving no
matter what and so you didn't grow up
and we're all alone in the world and
tried to find all of your secure
attachment and one person called a
romantic partner and then completely
freaked the out if they don't want
to be with you because you actually had
really secure attachment across a lot of
people and so again modern life nuclear
family homes private balance sheets
people are very lonely and very
disconnected and very overwhelmed and
trying to meet their social and
connection and attachment needs in way
too few of places so they're I mean we
could go we could do a whole show on
what aspects of indigenous wisdom need
reincorporated in the modern world
without regressing right we're not
talking about giving up technology we
are talking about reincorporating some
things that were lost in the transition
to a new kind of world structure that is
different and better than either modern
or pre-modern right and so on the other
side of the spectrum what are the things
that the ancient cultures figured out
that we can actually do better or
enhance with currently available
technology so many things so for
instance let's take our Vedic medicine
or Chinese medicine or any ancient
system of medicine they were developed
in a time in a place with some people
right and so even if they were amazing
at that time they were gonna apply to
the genetics of those people and the
kinds of things in their environment and
the health issues they face so so for
instance I happen to have celiac right
genetic predisposition to severe gluten
intolerance I had some pretty severe gut
issues I didn't know what it was about
when I was about 18 I went to see some
of the top Ayurvedic doctors in the
world
and they had helped a lot of people I
knew they saved my mom's life when
medical doctors had diagnosed her
terminal
they've done great things but they
diagnosed me with a Botts a disorder
which was you know the worldview that
they see through and so one of the
things that I needed were heavy foods
and they gave me as an example chapatis
flat breads with a lot of oil
well the flat breads were made of wheat
and they would have killed me if I was
eating lots of them but there was no
such thing as Indians with gluten
intolerance it was a genetic thing that
was outside of that whole worldview
right and simultaneously if we start
looking at heavy metal exposure or
exposure to plastics or PCBs or styrenes
or phthalates or you know pesticides all
the kinds of toxic exposure we have that
can affect cancer neurodegenerative you
know endocrine issues the ancient
systems aren't going to know what to do
with those things do they weren't part
of their environment so I would say you
know knowing what the genome is is kind
of a big deal having clinical chemistry
being able to do imaging like these are
really big deals is we don't die from
infectious disease for the most part
acute infectious disease anymore because
just hygiene and antibiotics and like
that actually serve a role in in
medicine painkillers you know like you
it's important that people can endure
pain discomfort sometimes to have
emotional resilience but painkillers for
dentistry are pretty awesome you know
compared to not simultaneously we can
say like following Western prices stuff
that the indigenous people didn't need
as much dentistry before they got
Western diet that's also true but there
are heaps of places where we have let's
even take EEG neurofeedback
there are many Buddhist monks who've
went and worked with neurofeedback and
found two things one they found that
students could get trained to go into
certain states of experience much faster
with the neurofeedback than they could
with just traditional Buddhist practice
and they even found that some of the
very advanced Buddhist meditators got
insights about their meditation that
they hadn't had
decades previously so I mean I don't
think almost any of us would say all
right let's trade and go live in
indigenous culture even though there's
so many upsides right because there's
also so many upsides to modern
technological life but to be able to
advance and integrate both is a great
thing
along the lines of rites of passage that
you brought up earlier I think some of
the basic ones like the rites of passage
to become an adult you know becoming a
teenager are pretty obvious but what
would you say that are in the context of
our modern technology and world would be
a good idea to create as a new rite of
passage for example like the day you're
allowed to use your cell phone or
something being a cultural thing to be
using social media in a responsible and
effective way that's you know you're not
addicted to notifications and that sort
of thing I would say it is a great
inquiry for us to think about the rites
of passage did have a lot to do with
both making some sure someone was
prepared for a certain kind of
responsibility and predisposing them to
handle it well and so as we get is we
have the technological capacity to be
more affected by our tech and to affect
more in the world through our tech to
you know we both need to prepare we both
need to build the tech better itself so
you know Tristan Harris and others are
talking a lot about how we we're
building text it is actually really
mostly bad for humans right that is
optimizing blue-screen clickbait
dopamine addiction for people with
really shitty attention spans and
distraction issues and like we actually
need to build the tech differently
itself because again this is like this
is a gaming mechanics thing if I'm
focused on how do I get the most number
of clicks and the most time on sight
that's not gonna make the happiest
people right and the happiest people are
gonna come do their and then
probably leave and do different kinds of
behavior that are not focused on driving
clicking on ADD so if I learn how to
hijack their dopamine opioid responds
this is a bad thing so part of it is
that we actually just have to develop
the technology differently
and again that gets back into the theory
of incentives right so just like with
the pharmaceuticals if the incentives of
the tech developers are not exactly
aligned with the well-being of the
people that the tech is being developed
for we're gonna get a deep mismatch
right mm-hmm so anywhere that incentive
and well-being is misaligned that
externality gap is a problem and with
exponential tech capacity that
externality gap becomes a catastrophic
problem but I think also preparing
people to handle the responsibility of
tech better is a meaningful part of it
and so I would be very curious to see
what the right rites of passage in the
future might look like this is why
blockchain has become such an
interesting thing for us because it it's
a different way of looking at building
these technologies while removing the
incentives to optimize for a single
entity you know for example clickbait
time on site that sort of thing so I
picture using the blockchain to develop
an operating system for a phone that
would be open-source and people could
develop something like maybe making
adblock and that sort of thing native to
the phone right and then you know
building in a whole operating system
around this principle of we're gonna
make it better for the human and then I
also picture having sort of the rites of
passage and rituals built into that
operating system - right so now let's
expend this one step and I'll say the
the big picture of how I think about
neural hacking is everything in your
environment is affecting you right this
concept of ontological design that we
build environments and they in turn
affect us like that's the fascinating
thing is that natural selection is
creatures that are being selected for
based on their adaptiveness to an
environment where the first creature
that radically changes its environment
even one generation to the next but then
we're making an environment that is in
turn affecting us back and since we
can't genetically change that fast we
are you know neuro structurally changing
epigenetics is changing and so when you
think about everything right you think
about the color and the Khan
on your phone you think about the fact
that it's two-dimensional rather than
three-dimensional you think about just
how much time we spend looking at a
fixed focal distance you know on our
laptop or whatever and that's a big part
of why we lose our eyesight because our
eyes are spending too much time looking
at a fixed focal distance rather than
then having a continuously changing
focal distance part of our evolutionary
environment but you move from that to
even thinking about okay so we're in a
house where the paint is filled full of
volatile organic compounds and the
carpet is made out of with volatile
organic compounds that aldehydes and etc
that are either in Decrypter carcinogens
or neurotoxins and our indoor air
quality is worse than freeway air
quality we need to completely change the
building materials we use right and then
you think well so those indigenous
people spent very little time indoors so
one of the effects was that they didn't
have a ceiling above their head most of
the time right and so they looked up at
the sky alot if you're in a 8 foot
ceiling you just don't look up a lot the
actual neurological your eyes going up
in your head going up stimulates your
brain in different ways that are
involved in the creative process and awe
and etc so everything from like the
physical structure of our buildings to
the structure of our digital spaces to
colors to chemistry you know of houses
of the entire built world we're building
it for a very small number of metrics
right like how many cubic feet can we
enclose how cheaply etc but when we
start thinking about that it's all
affecting the humans inside and we say
well how would I build a house where my
primary metric was optimizing the
Enlightenment and well-being of the
human that was inside along with the
well-being of the environment I love
this I wish you could see UV space while
you're talking right now it's just
fireworks but now it's the question
about how do we rebuild the entire human
built world to optimize for the thriving
of all life right to optimize for the
psychology and the physiology of all the
and the non-human life and have a built
world that reflects the design integrity
of the natural world you know when when
you look at in nature a hand is
optimizing for a million functions at a
time it's not optimizing for a few right
and it's also optimizing for its own
adaptive capacity to do so many things
if we start to understand what the
difference between complex and
complicated systems and learn how to
actually grow complex systems right the
how to do complex system design we're
designing across a lot more parameters I
actually think that's a fair way to
think about what humanity's task today
is it's to rebuild all of civilization
from scratch meaning our monetary
incentives our social status systems our
houses our digital environments the
physical infrastructure all of it to
rebuild it all from scratch aligned with
thinking about all of its effects
internalizing all the externalities
think about all of its effects and say
what's going to produce the most
thriving of the human and non-human life
that connects with this system across
all metrics of thriving that's our task
well
mind blown yeah so we might be reaching
the end of our time here but this brings
up another really interesting point of
focus for maybe a future episode is
talking about what you guys are doing
with neuro hacker collective and sort of
the big picture systems approach you're
taking the mothership yeah well I think
we have flagged a few follow-up
conversations on just this conversation
already so we've got the hard problem of
consciousness and existentialism maybe
some deeper stuff about what is good in
indigenous wisdom I think we talked
about briefly before the show what does
transhumanism look like in this
framework what is a kind of
transhumanism that is optimizing for
thriving across all metrics and that
understands the complex complicated
distinction and maybe how we're thinking
about all those things and what we're
doing neural hackers so it sounds like
we have
some conversations ahead definitely
fantastic cool well let's wrap up there
then Daniel is really good to have you
on the show again
minds blown I think we're gonna be
talking about this for weeks
and I offer one more thought about what
you all are doing in your show sure we
have so many more apocalyptic and
dystopian visions for our future than we
do
possibly viable proto pick ones so when
you guys you know are thinking about and
sharing the show what are positive
visions of a future if we share positive
visions of a future that aren't actually
tenable right they they aren't actually
anti fragile in the presence of
exponential tech or they presuppose
things that involve going backwards in
ways that would never be selected for
those are useless but to have more
humans visioning what is a viable
thriving civilization aligned with our
evolving capacities what could it look
like I think that's actually one of the
most critical things that has to be
happening more for Humanity to make it
and for those positive visions to come
about completely agree there's two sort
of key tenants that we have discussed so
much in the past which is behind our
thinking about future thinkers which is
you don't create a better future by
visualizing the worst case scenario all
the time and not thinking of the actual
thing that you want yes and that works
across the board with business with
anything that we've had experience you
know creating our lifestyle just like
you can look at our lifestyles in the
fact that we've traveled for five years
and basically done anything on a whim
that we've desired to do because that's
the thing we go after we visualize what
would be great how what would improve
our lives then we go after that thing
and then the second thing is not being
uncomfortable with discomfort and and
negative possibilities of the future as
well and actually spending the time to
incorporate antifragility like you said
and recovering from negative situations
into your plan for the future yeah so I
think that that is you made that point
earlier in the show and I think that is
huge and we keep harping on this lately
that you have to in order to be
resilient you have to actually be
comfortable with being uncomfortable yes
definitely well I'm delighted to see the
direction that the show keeps taking and
delighted to be on I look forward to the
next time - cool thanks for joining us
again this is always fun thank you so to
get the show notes with the links
mentions books etc go to future thinkers
org slash 43 and to listen to the first
half of this interview you can go to
future thinkers org slash 42 if you
haven't heard our first interview with
Daniel about the global phase shift then
go to future thinkers org slash 36 and
if you're interested in trying qualia
the smart drug stack that Daniels
company has developed go to future
thinkers that work slash brain hack
alright we'll see you in the next
episode bye bye thanks for listening to
the future thinkers podcast to get
notified of new podcasts and videos go
to future thinkers org and subscribe to
our mailing list you can also find us on
iTunes stitcher and you tube if you like
what we do and you want to help us make
more podcasts and videos give us a like
or review share it with your friends and
consider becoming a patron go to
patreon.com/crashcourse inori org slash
path last but not least if you want to
get access to more content hidden
episodes or if you just want to chat
with us in previous guests then check
out our community at community dark
future thinkers org
[Music]